<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Counsel for sufferers, or Helps under sufferings from [sic]</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02407</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6514B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R227098</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53299017</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53299017</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179792</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02407)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179792)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2803:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Counsel for sufferers, or Helps under sufferings from [sic]</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed, for Joseph Hall ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Wing C6514B</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Suffering --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:179792:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179792:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>COUNSEL FOR SUFFERERS, OR Helps under Sufferings from.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 5:41.</bibl>
               <p>And they departed from the preſence of the Councel, rejoycing that they were counted worthy to ſuffer shame for his name.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Sapienti meliora ſunt in votis, deteriora vero in expectatione: Plut: de tranquil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gravius eſt vulnus quod non expectatur, &amp; illa agrius tollerantur, quibus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſe non prius aſſue facit. Aug.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> printed, for JOSEPH HALL, Book-ſeller, &amp; Book-binder, on Tine-Bridg New Caſtle upon Tine, 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:179792:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179792:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian READER.</head>
            <p>CHriſtian Reader, I nothing doubt; but the worthy Author will be in eſteem with, and get the approbation and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of all that either now are, or hereafter may be tryſted with a ſuffering lot for their owning of, and cleaving to the truths of Jeſus Chriſt, for his plain, free, and faithfull endeavours in the following treatiſe. It needs no teſtimony from man to an impartiall Reader; for it is ſtampt with ſuch a divine image, and bearing ſuch clear lineaments of heaven-born truths, as teſtify it to be of God, and therefore oblidgeth us to receive it, as into our houſes, ſo into our hearts.</p>
            <p>Further, I make bold to tell thee, Reader, who ever thou art; if thou haſte received a ſpirituall relish, thou shalt taſte much ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in this (it being ſo ſutable and ſeaſonable) following diſcourſe which clears up theſe ſix, ſolid, ſound and moſt neceſſary propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions.</p>
            <p>Firſt; That the condition of Gods people in this world is a ſuffering condition. To ſuffer, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that shame is one great peice of, and ingredient in their ſufferings. To ſuffer shame, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that the profeſsion of Chriſt's name is the great ground of the ſaints ſufferings. To ſuffer shame for his name, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, It is a great dignation of God to call out his people to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for his name. Worthy to ſuffer shame for his name, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, that an opportunity to ſuffer shame for the name of Chriſt, ought to be eſteemed and entertained not onely willingly, but joyfully. Rejoycing that they were counted worthy to ſuffer shame for his name, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Sixthly. The conſideration of Chriſts name being in our ſufferings, is ſufficient to quicken us to joyfullneſs in them. And they departed, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:179792:3"/>
            <p>In the handling of which, it may be truely ſaid of the Author. (Alluding to that Prov. <hi>31: 29.</hi> many Daughters have done ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly, but thou excelleſt them all) if there be any thing wanting here which happily thou might have exſpected impute it to the want of the Authors hand &amp; ſubſcription how ever I would not keep from thee what is here, though I could not give thee what is wanting.</p>
            <p>It is ſtoried of Democritus, that he put out his eyes that he might contemplate the better; I doe not counſel thee to doe ſoe, but if ye would wink with one; the eye of carnall reaſon and ſlavish fear (captivate every thought to the obedience of Chriſt,) thou might with that other of faith, take the better aime at the marke to obtaine the price of the high calling in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Thus not willing longer to detaine thee from the perusall of the Book it ſelf, I commend both thee and it to the bleſſing of God, and bids yow fare wel.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:179792:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Acts Cap. 5. verſ. 41.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And they departed from the preſence of the Councel, rejoycing that they were Counted worthy to ſuffer shame for his Name.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the ſaying of Bishop Jewel, that famous and shining light of our Church: That it becomes a Bishop, or Miniſter of the Ghoſpel to die preaching. It was Auſtins wish of old. That he might die, either preaching or praying. Accordingly wee finde the Apoſtles in this chapter preaching in the face of death it's ſelf; wee finde them breathing out Gods grace to man, while they are breathing out their lives into the Armes of Gods grace. Commending of God to the world, while they live in the world, yea when they were leaving of the world; while the world per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute Chriſt, the Apoſtles preach him.</p>
            <p>It was a tyme of great oppoſition and publick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution; as yee may read in the Hiſtory of this Book, yea of this very chapter; But the Apoſtles continued in the work of the Ghoſpel: They went not a foot of the way of their Calling and ſtation, notwithſtanding all the malice of their enemies, but continued the ſame by many ſigns and miracles, for by the hands of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,<note place="margin">Chap. 5.12.13.</note> were many ſigns and wonders wrought among the people; ſo as their perſons received honour, and a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:179792:4"/>great acceſſion was made unto the Church by their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry. God will not own his people in haltion dayes, but in ſtormy and tempeſtuous times. Paul that was once a great perſecutor, after converſion, turns a great preacher and profeſſor; Grace where it comes, makes a great change, and the Croſs of Chriſt is the beſt Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit; to read a Lecture of Gods grace to ſouls out off: But the High Prieſts and officers (alwayes the ſevereſt enemies of Chriſt and Religion) if they prove not of, and with the people, who commonly follow their heads that go before them) if the Apoſtles cannot now keep their mouths shut, they'l endeavour to keep their perſons cloſe; wicked men who cannot hinder the burning of holineſs in wardly in the hearts of Gods people, will (if poſſible) hinder the shinning of it openly in their lives. They laid hands on the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and put them in the common priſon.<note place="margin">V. 18.</note> The worſt (if any thing could be worſe then another) as for them; But while their mouths are shewing forth Gods praiſe, He opens a Doore for their deliverance. But the Angel of the Lord by night,<note place="margin">V. 19.</note> opened the priſon doors and brought them forth. He makes his Angels inſtruments of their deliverance; yea, and he doth not onely deliver them out of priſon, but immediatly ſets them to work again, which they did accept: and fell to work again immediatly;<note place="margin">V. 21.</note> and when they heard that they entered into the Temple again early and taught,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:179792:4"/>they Eccho'd to the voice, they were journey-men at Gods call ready; no ſooner could he command, but they were ready to obey in whatſoever he would have them to doe. God ow'ns them and adviſes them, gives new orders to them. Mans interdiction, cannot hinder Gods commiſſion, nor invalidate his commands. Moſes goes in again and again to Pharaoh, notwithſtanding of all his threatnings againſt him; ſo do the Apoſtles here fall too and follow their work, what ever was threatned againſt them; but no ſooner had they got into the Temple, but the high Prieſt and his train, was at their heeles; called Councel, and finding them not in the priſon but in the Temple: they ſaid unto them, did not wee ſtraitly command you, that yee should not teach in his name; and behold yee have filled Jeruſalem with your Doctrine, and intend to bring this Mans blood upon us. A guilty conſcience was within, and they could not endure the Doctrine of the Ghoſpel. Peter there turns prolocutor, and he makes a noble and brave anſwer unto them: ſaying, wee ought to obey God raither then Man. The commands of no inferiour power, can ſuperſede the commands of a ſuperiour power; and now orders were iſſued out againſt the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, to forbid their preaching; yet, having an injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction upon them from Chriſt they go on; yea, Peter goes on and preaches a Sermon before his enemies, and did not onely preach what might ſerve the turne, (was
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:179792:5"/>not mealy mouthed) but preached that, which touched them to the quick,<note place="margin">V. 29, 30. and 31.</note> tells them that that Jeſus that was now exalted, whom they now preached, that very Jeſus they had crucified: ſo he goes on to the 31 verſe. The God of our Fathers raiſed one Jeſus whom yee ſlew, and hanged on a Tree. And now they begin to think, not of in priſoning, but of maſſacring them; as if the land were not able to bear their perſons, and what they had ſaid was the higheſt peice of wickedneſs in the world. They go about to kill their bodies, that would (if poſible) ſave their ſouls. And being cutt to the heart: they now take councel together to ſlay them; but one of the councel, being more wiſe then the reſt, gives more ſober advice, which upon mature deliberation (though not out of conſcience but fear) they took; But yet they would give them ſome taſte of their kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. They called the Apoſtles and beat them,<note place="margin">V. 40.</note> and then let them go. And doe but ſee the effects in the 41. and 42. verſ. And they departed from the preſence of the Councel, rejoycing that they were counted worthy, to ſuffer shame for his Name. And daily in the Temple, and in every houſe, they ceaſed not to teach, and to preach Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The words that I have read contain. 1. an account of Gods dignation towards his people, and their diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition towards him. The ſaints condition (to ſuffer) the name, or title of their ſufferings, (shame.)</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:179792:5"/>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly here is their diſpoſition of ſpirit, not with ſorrow, and hanging down their heads like a bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rush, no they lift up their heads, and exalt their horn in him.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.20.</note> It was a manlike act in David when the child was dead: while it was alive, he faſted and wept: But when it was dead he aroſe from the earth, washed and anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf, and changed his apparel and came into the houſe of the Lord, and worshipped; ſo it was with the Apoſtles, notwithſtanding all their evill uſages; yet, they rejoyced that they were counted worthy to ſuffer shame for his name.</p>
            <p>Six propoſitions containe the ſum of this Text.<note place="margin">6 Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Prop. </seg>1</label> Firſt, that the condition of Gods people, in this world, is a ſuffering condition. (To ſuffer.)</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Prop. </seg>2</label> Secondly, that shame is one great peece of, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredient in, their ſufferings. (To ſuffer shame.)</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Prop. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, that the profeſſion of Chriſts name, is the great ground of the ſaints ſufferings. To ſuffer shame for his name.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Prop. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, it is a great dignation of God to call out his people to ſuffer for his name (worthy to ſuffer shame for his name.)</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Prop. </seg>5</label> Fifthly, that an opportunity to ſuffer shame, for the name of Chriſt: ought to be eſteemed, and entertained, not onely willingly, but joy-fully (rejoycing that they were counted worthy to ſuffer shame for his name.)</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Prop. </seg>6</label> Sixthly, the conſideration of Chriſts name being in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:179792:6"/>our ſufferings, is ſufficient to quick en us up to joyfullneſs in them. And they departed &amp;c.</p>
            <div n="1" type="proposition">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> First, the ſaints condition in the world is a ſuffering condition; the ſufferings of the ſaints and people of God ariſe from the Devil, and from the wicked world. The dragon was wroth with the woman,<note place="margin">Rev. 12. v. laſt.</note> and went to make war with the remnant of her ſeed. The dragon is the Devil, the woman the church. By his inſtruments he maks war with her, the ſeed of the ſerpent, makes war with the ſeed of the woman, becauſe they keep the commandments of God, and have the Teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt: It was a right ſpeech of Auſtin, when thoſe ten perſecuting emperors were dead, and thoſe ten perſecutions over, and the people began to comfort themſelves, that perſecution would now ceaſe, O but ſaith he, the Devil is not dead, and ſoe long as he hath inſtruments to ſtir up, perſecution will be raiſed. So long as the wicked luſt to envy, the people of God muſt expect to ſuffer.<note n="1" place="margin">1. Reaſon of our ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> They that cannot ſin, muſt expect to ſuffer, becauſe we have ſined, wee ſuffer juſtly from God, becauſe wee will not ſin, wee ſuffer unjuſtly from men. Never a ſoul that ever ſet it's face towards heaven, but the world turned their backs upon it: The Church of Chriſt, is as the Lylie among thorns, ſuch as are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted in the Love of God, muſt expect to feel the wrath and anger of men;<note place="margin">John. 16.33.</note> in the world (it was Chriſts own prediction) ye shall have tribulation; in the upper
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:179792:6"/>Region above is peace, but in this under the moon is nothing but trouble. Daniel,<note place="margin">Dan. 6.16.</note> a man greatly beloved of God, but as greatly perſecuted by men. The Apoſtle Paul, a perſon eminent in grace and in favour with God, yet notwithſtanding, as the raither extreamly perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted; he was in bonds for the word ſake. 2 Tim. 2.9. Wherein I ſuffer trouble as an evil doer, even unto bonds. They that receive much mercy from God,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.9.</note> and performe much duty to God; muſt expect to meet with little mercy from the world. They shall put you out of the Synagogue, yea, out of the world too, kill you and yet think they doe God good ſervice; this ariſeth from the words wickedneſs, they wound Chriſt through the Saints ſides; ungodly men conceive and contrive enmity againſt the people of God, and when it is conceive, it bringeth forth reproach, and perſecution of them. Lord,<note place="margin">Iſa. 26.11.</note> when thy hand is lifted up, they will not ſee: but they shall ſee, and be ashamed for their envy at the people, yea, the fire of thine enemies shall devour them. The whole world lyeth in wickedneſs, that is, the two ſeeds are put in enmity, the ſeed of the ſerpent againſt the ſeed of the woman.</p>
               <p>Secondly, from Gods will and pleaſure,<note n="2" place="margin">2. Rea. of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering.</note> God hath will'd ſufferings to his people, as his Livery, its a Legacy to his people, to you it is given on the behalf of Chriſt: not onely to beleive, but alſo to ſuffer: not onely to beleive, but to blood alſo: They that are called to grace,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:179792:7"/>are call'd to ſufferings. The tyme of grace at firſt is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme of love, the continuance of it, a tyme of affliction. For whom he did foreknow,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.29.</note> he alſo did predeſtinate to be conformed to the Image of his ſon; that is his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Image, in order to our conformity to his glorious Image. God had one Son without ſin, but he hath none without a ſcourge. It is the will of God wee should be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Chriſt; not onely in the end, and forme, but in the means. Sin reſembles a man to the Devil, but ſufferings reſembles a man to Chriſt. From hence.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Con∣ſidera∣tion. </seg>1</label> Firſt, conſider, ye had need look you be right in the way of your profeſſion, leaſt while ye ſuffer for God, ye alſo ſuffer from God. It will be a ſad thing to be caſt out of earth for making a profeſſion; and to be caſt out of heaven for making no more then a profeſſion: to ſuffer for Chriſt here on earth, and to ſuffer from Chriſt hereafter in Hell to eternity. Look that ye be right in your profeſſion, and ye will finde comfort in your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Con∣ſid. </seg>2</label> Secondly, if the ſaints muſt ſuffer from the world, then let them not ſuffer from one another; if the beaſts of the forreſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 22.12.</note> the bulls of Bashan push at them, let not the Lambs push one at another. Doe they ſuffer from the world? That is no great matter, but to ſuffer from familiar friends, is too much. If it had been mine enemy (ſaith David) I could have born it:<note place="margin">Pſal. 55.12, 13. and 41.9. v.</note> but it was thou my familiar friend, who took ſweet councel together, &amp;c.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:179792:7"/>It is ſaid in a propheſie of Chriſt. Zech. 13.6. v. He was wounded in the houſe of his friends; that augment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the grief.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Con∣ſid. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, let every man then enter the liſts of profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but with an expectation of ſufferings and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> The bullet may miſs you, it's an ill Battel were none 'ſcapes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> But it may hit you as well, it's ſtrange; if a man will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus, if he don't ſuffer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, either by the tongues or by the hands of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men. It was an excellent ſpeech of the Lord Brook, that he that undertakes in the way of Chriſtianity, it is a vain thing for him to think of ſaving any thing but his ſoul; ye may be call'd out to reſiſt unto Blood ſtriveing againſt ſin, and as Gods mercy towards the end of the Churches troubles, will be ſweeteſt: ſo the Devil's rage will be greateſt: and though ye have had halcyon dayes of peace, and have but the prick of a pin inſteed of the point of a ſword, yee may yet, meet with the tail of the ſtorme, the worſt may be behinde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="proposition">
               <head>
                  <hi>Second propoſition is this.</hi> That reproach and shame, is part of Gods peoples ſufferings here in the world.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> It is their portion, a peculiarity of the ſaints, to ſuffer shame for Chriſts ſake. They that are highly eſteemed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:179792:8"/>with God, are commonly caſt out with men. They lie here oft-tymes among the pots, whom God intends for the faireſt Cup-board of heavenly glory in the world to come. They manifeſted open indignity to the Apoſtles, two ſeverall wayes; by words and by blows reproach before Magiſtrats, is a shame in the worlds Calender. Thoſe whom God doe honour; one way or another the wicked will dishonour: The wickeds ſpight is againſt god, but, Panther-like, if they can't reach the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, they'l tear the picture; though the conſciences of Gods people compurgats them, yet the world maks no conſcience of condemning.<note place="margin">Pſal. 44.13.</note> Thou makeſt us a reproach to our neighbours, a ſcorn and deriſion to them that are round about us. A reproach to men on every ſide hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in, and compaſſed about with reproaches, ſcandals, and ſlanders,<note place="margin">Pſal. 79.4.</note> ſo Pſal. 79. v. 4. wee are become a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to our neighbours, aſcorn and a deriſion to them that are round about us. You ſee the church of God, where-ever, at one tyme or other, were under reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Iſaac the Son of the promiſe, was ſcoffed at, by Ishmael,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.29.</note> this is called perſecution. But as then he that was born after the flesh, perſecuted him that was born after the ſpirit; ſo it is now. Thus it was with holy Job when he was made an out caſt by his friends;<note place="margin">Job. 16.8, 9.</note> that made of him no more then a Hypocrite: He teareth me in his wrath, who hateth me: he gnasheth upon me with his teeth; mine enemy sharpneth his eyes upon me. They
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:179792:8"/>gaped upon me with their mouth, they have ſmitten me upon the cheek reproachfully, they have gathered themſelves together againſe me. And will ye ſtep a little farther and ſee David. In my adverſity they rejoyced &amp;c. this was the meaſure this holy man of God met with in his tyme; and the Prophet Iſa: ſaith,<note place="margin">Iſa. 8.18.</note> that the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of his tyme were ſigns and wonders in Iſrael<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Zion is an out caſt, whom no man ſeeks after an out caſt that no man ſeeks after.<note place="margin">Jer. 30.17. Lam. 1.7, 21.</note> So Jeruſalem what she came to be in her diſtreſſes. They have heard that I ſight, there is none to comfort me: all mine enemies have heard of my trouble, they are glad that thou haſt done it: And this Is common with all the ſaints, for ſuch as are guilty of oppreſſion,<note place="margin">Lam. 2: 15, 16.</note> are guilty likewiſe of Columnies ſo chap. 2. is this the city of ſolemnities? All that paſs by clap their hands at thee; they hiſs and wag their head at the daughter of Jeruſalem, ſaying, is this the city that men call, the perfection of beauty, the joy of the whole earth? All thine enemies have opened their mouth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee: they hiſs and gnash the teeth; they ſay, wee have ſwallow'd her up; certainly this is the day that wee looked for; wee have found, wee have ſeen it: Thus they pleaſe themſelves, with ſcoffing at the poor Church and people of God.<note place="margin">Pſal. 69.20. Lam. 3.30.</note> Reproaches have broken my heart; ſaith the Pſalmiſt in the perſon of Chriſt: ſo Lam: The church there ſaith, she gave her cheeks to him that ſmot her, she was filled full ith reproaches.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:179792:9"/>Thus both the worship and worshippers of God, have been made a reproach in the world. The word of the Lord in the propheſie of Jer. 6.10. was a reproach unto that wicked generation;<note place="margin">Jer. 6.10.</note> to whom shall I ſpeak, and give warning, that they may hear; behold, the word of the Lord is unto them a reproach: they have no delight in it:<note place="margin">Jer. 20. v. 18.</note> and ſo chap. 20.18. he ſpeaks again of the reproaches he met withall, there he ſaith, he came forth out of the womb to ſee labour and ſorrow, that his dayes should be conſumed with shame: The ſpirit of God tells the Prophet Ezekiel,<note place="margin">Ezek. 33.30.</note> concerning the children of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, not enemies onely, but the children of the people are taking againſt thee, by the wall's, and in the doors of the houſes, they ſnarld at the word of the Lord. Thus all the Prophets under the old, and Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles under the New Teſtament, have been accounted vilely off. Paull call'd a ſeditious fellow, Chriſt called the Carpenters Son, no better title could they afford him: And they thought they had hit the bird on the eye, when they ſaid have any of the Rulers beleived on him!<note place="margin">Iſa. 66. v. 5.</note> Eſa. 66.5. Your brethren that hated you, that caſt yow out for my name ſake ſaid, let the Lord be glorified. Therefore the Apotle exhorts. Peter. 2.12. Having your converſation honeſt among the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, that whereas they ſpeak againſt you as evill doers, they may by your good works,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.12.</note> which thy shall behold, glorify God in the day of your viſitation. The ſaints
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:179792:9"/>had need doe well, while they hear it. The work of God, as well as the ſervants of God, hath met with reproaches. Neh. 2.19.<note place="margin">Nehem. 2.19.</note> But when Sanballat the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norite, and Tobiah the ſervant the Ammonite, and Geshem the Arabian heard it, they laughed us to ſcorn, and deſpiſed us, and ſaid, what is this thing that ye doe? will ye rebell againſt the King? there was a charge for them. So chap. 4.2, 8.<note place="margin">Neh 4.2, 8.</note> And he ſpake before his breth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, and the Army of Samaria, and ſaid, what doe theſe feeble Jews? will they fortify themſelves? will they ſacrifice? will they make an end in a day? will they revive the ſtones out of the heaps of the rubbish, which are burnt? And v. 8.<note place="margin">v. 8.</note> And conſpired all of them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to come and to feight againſt Jeruſalem, and to hinder it. In ſo much, as they even broke the good mans heart, and made him cry out v. 4. Hear, O our God, for wee are deſpiſed: and turne their reproach upon their own head, and give them for a prey in the land of Captivity. The Apoſtles, when they were preaching the Ghoſpel; with greateſt earneſtneſs and vehemencie, nay, when as the holie Ghoſt, deſcended in ſuch an extraordinary manner upon them, they ſaid, theſe men are fill'd with new wine, therefore the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, they were defamed, and blaſphemed,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.13.</note> wee are made as the filth of the world, and are the off-ſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of all things. This is the Sect, every where ſpoken againſt. Heb. 10.33.<note place="margin">Acts 28.22.</note> You may read, concerning thoſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:179792:10"/>admirable worthies, what a heap of reproaches were thrown upon them. Partly whileſt ye were made a gazing ſtock, both by reproaches and afflictions. And Heb. 11.36.<note place="margin">Heb. 11.36.</note> And others had tryal of cruel mockings, and ſcourgings, yea, moreover, of bonds and impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And indeed reproaches are cruel, the wounds of the tongue, goe deeper, then thoſe of the hand; and in the primitive tymes, how many calumnies were the precious ſervants of the moſt high God, loaden with; when they roſe early in the morning to ſing their morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hymne, they charged them with uncleanneſs, and inceſt: thus they call'd Athenaſius the eldeſt Son of the Devil, And Luther (the Papiſts ſay) was the cauſe of all the troubles, that befell Germany. With vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying names and expreſſions, have Gods eminent and worthy Champions ſuffered. So for uſage too, what whippings, ſcourgings, impriſonning? thus it was with Chriſt; and thus it was with all his followers. The deſigne of the adverſary, hath been, partly the terrour, and partly, the shame of Chriſtians. They were tortured,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.35.</note> not accepting deliverance, that they might obtaine a better reſurrection. This was the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (my beloved) of the eminent Saints, and people of God of old; and the reaſon of this is plain.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Firſt, becauſe the excellency of the people of God, is an hidden excellency, it is no wonder, that the world reproach that they doe not underſtand. Many men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:179792:10"/>out of malice will reproach that they doe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, but it's no wonder the world reproach that they doe not underſtand; our life is hid, with Chriſt in God: Religion is a melancholly thing, ſayes the men of the world, and therefore: it's no wonder they deſpiſe it: as it was ſaid of Chriſt:<note place="margin">Jeſ. 53.3.</note> He was deſpiſed and rejected of men, a man of ſorrows, and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with grief: And ſo it is with all the people of God; men look upon their outſides, and ſee that vil'd, but they ſee not their inſides.<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.13.</note> The Kings Daughter is all glorious within.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Secondly, ſometymes from their envy at the Saints excellency, there is a Contraſtation, and oppoſition, between the Children of God, and the men of the world, in poynt of excellency. Men will endeavour to darken and obſcure the glory of Gods people, and by obſcuring their graces, they think their own leſſer lights will appear the more glorious; The Saints ſtand in their light: therefore they cannot endure them. They are like a houſe, ſtanding in the light of another, and they will endeavour, to take it down, and this is a cunning way, to perſecute the people of God: and hereby; they exceedingly hinder many ſouls from embraceing Religion; and damp the ſpirits of ſuch as would profeſs it. I have read of one, that comming to be baptized, and ſeeing none, but a company of poor Chriſtians together, asked what they were, to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:179792:11"/>whom the Emperour anſwered, they were the ſervants of God, at which he went away, ſaying, if God kept his ſervants ſo poor, he would not be one of them. This is the trick of Apoſtates, to reproach zealous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, to take of the shame of their Apoſtacy, as Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian did.<note place="margin">Jer. 6.28.</note> They are all grievious revolters, that walk with ſlanders, they are Braſs and Iron, they are all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupters. Wel, hence Gods people may learn.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Leſſon. </seg>1</label> Firſt, what to expect in the world, shame and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, and they shall doe wel, to examine themſelves, whether they can own a perſecuted Chriſt: can'ſt thou own a crucified, a reproached Chriſt, a comdemned Chriſt? can'ſt thou own the way of holineſs when jeered at? truly it is a great temptation; when Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is become a byword, men are affraid, of publick ignominies. Many can't endure the term of preciſian, puritan, phannatik, for the enemy to shake his hand, as he paſſes by, ſaying, there is a puritan; it is a hard thing to ſome men.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 6.14 &amp; 22.</note> Can you ſay as David, when he danced before the Lord, when ſcoff't at by Michal. If this be to be vile, I will yet be more vile then thus, Conſider Chriſt, Chriſtians, that endured the Croſz, deſpiſed the shame, and is now ſet down, at the right hand of the Majeſty on high, far above all principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and powers, you muſt deny your ſelves, your own luſts, pleaſures, honours; if ye will be Chriſts Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples you muſt be willing to be accounted baſe, vile
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:179792:11"/>by every evill foot of pride, even by them, that in the flourish of Religion, ye would not ſet with the dogs of your flock, as Job ſpeaks.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Leſſ. </seg>2</label> Secondly, let this teach you,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.8.</note> to animate your ſelves againſt reproaches; be not thou aſham'd of the afflictions of the Ghoſpel. Nothing carry's with it a true ground of shame, but ſin; be not ye aſhamed of your afflictions. Moſes, choſe the reproaches of Chriſt, before the pleaſures, and treaſures of Egypt: wee muſt goe forth to Chriſt, without the Camp, to mount Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vary, as well as mount Olivet; bearing his reproach. And that you may be armed againſt reproaches.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>1</label> Firſt; Remember, you are bleſſed and honoured of Chriſt, while reproached, jeered and mocked by the world: and no matter though the dogs barke, ſo the Maſter gives good entertainment: Bleſſed are ye when men ſhal revile you, and ſpeak all manner of evil of you, falſly, for my ſake; yea, bleſſed are they which are perſecuted for righteouſneſs ſake, for their's is the Kingdome of God. It is a curſed thing to reproach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, but a bleſſed thing, to be reproached by another.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>2</label> Secondly, Chriſts name is a greater glory, then all your reproaches, can be dishonourable, to you that beleive Chriſt is an honour; you carry the Croſs of Chriſt, as a Banner diſplayed, and there is greater honour in that, then the world can reflect dishonour upon your for ſo doing.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:179792:12"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>3</label> Thirdly,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.14.</note> conſider, the ſpirit of glory reſts upon you, not the ſpirit of grace onely, but of glory alſo, not for a little tyme, but to reſt, yea, and that for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, conſider, you have aſſurance of a name in heaven, and therefore may willingly goe through dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour on earth. Your reproaches, are Chriſts reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Remember your names are written in heaven; and Chriſts raggs, are better then the worlds Robes, and ſeeing you have a name in the court, what matter though you have none in the country.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>5</label> Fifthly,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.7.</note> your Tryalls will be found for praiſe, and honour, and glory, at the appearance of Jeſus Chriſt: The wicked shall leave their names for a curſe unto my choſen: for the Lord God shal ſlay thee, and call his ſervants by another name.<note place="margin">Iſa. 65.15.</note> Thou shalt alſo be a crown of glory in the hand of the Lord, and a royall Diadem, in the hand of the God. Iſa. 62.3. The Lord hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to wipe away the rebuke of his people, and there shall be never a blott, to blurr their faces. The day is shortly comming, in which wicked men shall anſwer, for all their hard uſages of, and ſpeeches to the people of God.<note place="margin">Dan. 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.3. Math. 2.34.</note> The wicked that are in the higheſt ſtate, in the world, shall riſe at the laſt day to everlaſting shame, and you to everlaſting honour. Ye shall shine as the Sun, in the Kingdome of your father. The shouldier is not ashamed of his marks, and ſcarrs he receives in the wars, but looks upon them, as ſo many badges of honour:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:179792:12"/>ſo the reproaches you meet with, are but as ſo many badges of honour, all the ſcarrs yee meet with in the way of holyneſs, are as ſo many marks of honour put upon you, and if you confeſs Chriſt before men, he will confeſs you, before his father, and before the holy Angels. And O Chriſtians! here is a good target againſt reproaches, do but maintaine your innocency, and then you can never be made miſerable, by the Judgments of others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="proposition">
               <head>
                  <hi>Third propoſition is this.</hi> That the name of Chriſt, is the cauſe, and great occaſion, of all the ſufferings that befall the Children of God.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> The name of Chriſt: they rejoyced that they were counted worthy, to ſuffer shame for his name. You shall (ſaith our Saviour) be hated for my name ſake.<note place="margin">Math. 24.9.</note> All theſe things will they doe unto you for my names ſake.<note place="margin">John 15.21.</note> There's the ground of wicked mens malice againſt the ſaints; the profeſſion of Chriſt is the butt of perſecution: for that is thee imply'd, ſome ſuffer the loſs of Father and Mother, Brethren and Siſters, houſes and lands, for my names ſake, (ſaith Chriſt.) It's not for their ſin, that Gods people ſuffer from the world, but for their grace: could they conforme to the world, could they drink and be drunk, ſwear and blaſpheme, live riotouſly and looſly, the world would hug them in their Armes, and embrace them with their deareſt affection. They
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:179792:13"/>think it a ſtrange thing,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.3.</note> you run not with them to the ſame exceſs of ryot: This expreſſion (for his name ſake) may have a double reference.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Refer. </seg>1</label> Firſt; As it is the reaſon of the tolerableneſs of the Saints ſufferings, Chriſts name being in their ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, that bears them up under them; their love to Chriſts name, puts them upon accepting of ſufferings ſo joyfully.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.10.</note> Therefore I take pleaſure in reproaches, in neceſſities, in infirmities, in diſtreſſes for Chriſts That is that which ingages a Chriſtian in, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages him under ſufferings; and as ſufferings for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs diſtinguish a Saint from the wicked, ſo will reſpect to Chriſts Name diſtiguish a Saint from a Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite; for although I should give all my goods to the poor (a univerſall almes) and my body to be burned, yet if I had not charity, al were nothing; therefore for thy ſake (ſaith the Church) we are killed all the day long, wee are accounted as sheep for the ſlaughter. But,</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Refer. </seg>2</label> Secondly, I will underſtand it as the reaſon of the worlds infliction of reproaches, and perſecutions, upon the people of God: what ever the world pretend, it is for Chriſts ſake; for ſome thing of Chriſt with in them, that they hold forth, that they hate them for. Therefore the afflictions that befall them, are called the afflictions of the Ghoſpel:<note place="margin">Tim. 2.1.</note> It is a great ground of comfort to the ſaints, that it is for Chriſt's, and his Goſpel's ſake, that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:179792:13"/>they ſuffer. Doe not they blaſpheme,<note place="margin">James 2.7.</note> that worthy name, by the which ye are called? It was the name of Chriſt, that worthy name, they delt with them for. It was upon that account, they meaſured out this meaſure unto them. The world can't come up to the pitch of holyneſs the Saints doe, and they going beyond the common pace of Civility, Morality, and Hypocriſie, the Dogs barke at them. Noah condemned the old world, by his righteouſneſs: the world praiſe and canno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize the dead ſaints, but can't endure to ſee them that are living, but hunt after their precious lives. If one child in the Family have the Fathers indulgence, all the reſt will hate him. So Joſephs brethren hated him.<note place="margin">Gen 49.27.</note> He that is the object of Gods love, (commonly) is the but of the worlds envy, therefore the wicked take all the occaſions they can, againſt the ſaints, and watch for their haltings; they dayly blaſpheme the name of God, becauſe of his peoples failings.<note place="margin">Iſa. 52. v. 5, 6.</note> And the moſt of them are like Tyggers, that cannot endure a fragrant ſcent, but will fall upon them that carry it, and kill them. And if it be ſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> Firſt, then learn wee a good warrant, and juſt ground, of our ſufferings; Chriſts name. Many are not ſatisfyed to ſuffer, becauſe they think their ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings are not for Chriſts ſake: be ſure your ſufferings by for Chriſts ſake, elſe you cannot ſuffer conforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:179792:14"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, hence learn, the bitter hatred the world have, againſt Chriſt and his people: Religion hath alwayes brought forth the greateſt quarrels, though it leaſt deſerves it: I ame not to ſend peace, but a ſword; the ſtrictneſs of the "Ghoſpel cauſes perſecution, Satan hath ſo blinded the minds of men, and hardned their hearts, that this is moſtly the condition of the Saints here in the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, this condemnes the pretences of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that ſay, they perſecute the Saints, becauſe they are ſeditious, aud rebellious perſons, whereas it is, becauſe they won't be wicked, but religious: not becauſe they are traiterous to men, but becauſe they will not be trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous to heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>4</label> Fourthly, here is great encouragement to Chriſtians under ſufferings, Chriſts name is in their ſufferings, if it were upon the account of your own name, that you ſuffer, you ſhould doe well to lay them down in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but it is for thy ſake;<note place="margin">Rom. 8.36. 1 Cor. 4.10.</note> here is comfort, when the ſoul can ſay, Lord it is for thy ſake. The Apoſtle triumphs in this. That they were fooles for Chriſts ſake. O! bleſſed be God, that ever wee had a name to offer up for Chriſt,<note place="margin">Bernard ſaying.</note> and ſacrifice for Chriſt: As Bernard was wont to ſay, Lord make me a ſhield, to fence of the injuries, that fall upon thy name. Paul complain'd of his perſecuting the Saints, it is a killing the Prince of life, the Lord of glory; it is a great peece of Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:179792:14"/>It is not our preaching, but your not receiving the Goſpel ſaith Luther, that is the worſt ingredient in ſuffering.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="proposition">
               <head>
                  <hi>The fourth Propoſition is this:</hi> It is a great Dignation of God towards his people, to call them out, and count them worthy to ſuffer for Chriſts ſake.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>4</label> (They rejoyced that they were counted worthy) ſuch honour have not all men, no, nor all the Saints: doing work is honourable, but ſuffering worke is more honourable. The Apoſtle counts this a great gift,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.14.</note> next to beleiving; to declare Chriſts ſacrifice to others in the world. It is an honour to doe much, but greater honour to ſuffer much for Chriſt. God forbid I ſhould glory in any thing, ſave in the Croſs of Chriſt. The Apoſtle well underſtood what he did, and ſaid too. I glory (ſaith he) in nothing but the Croſs of Chriſt. To ſuffer for Chriſt, is an honour beyond that granted to the Angels, for they have no body, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Philpot would ſay of ſufferings, no ſuch preferment on Earth, as for Gods Childen to be called out to ſuffer. I have read of a Knight in Venice, that being carried to ſuffer with his other brethren, they being bound, and he being a noble perſon, was carried, without chains and fetters, why ſaith he, may not I be bound likewiſe, and ſo commence, Knight of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable order of the Garter? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>4</label> now ſufferings for Chriſt, they are honourable.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:179792:15"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> Firſt, becauſe they are a part of our conformity to Chriſt, not to fill up the perſonal ſufferings of Chriſt; that were blaſphemy to affirm, nor yet his ſufferings in order to the ſatisfaction of divine juſtice, but the myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſufferings of Chriſt for edification; this is a drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſts cup, and a fullfilling after him: it is a greater honour to be like a crucify'd, then 'tis to be like a glorifyed Chriſt; becauſe moſt of our happineſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in our conformity to Chriſt: which is in ſuffering for him, and in order to being glorifyed with him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Refer. </seg>2</label> Secondly, it is a bearing wittneſs to Chriſt, and Gods taking your Teſtimony, and this is a great honour. Yee are my wittneſſes,<note place="margin">Iſa. 43.12.</note> ſaith the Lord, that I am God: here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Saints obtaine victory over their accuſers, by the blood of the Lamb,<note place="margin">Rev. 12.11.</note> and the word of their Teſtimony. Paull was Gods wittneſs, and God made him a choſen veſſel to bear his name.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, becauſe it admits a man into ſpecial fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowship with Chriſt. Paul preſt after the fellowship with Chriſts ſufferings.<note place="margin">Phil. 3.12.</note> By the ſpirit of life and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, implanted in beleivers, they have a fellowship with Chriſt, and ſtill (a nearer) by ſufferings, which the Apoſtle preſſeth after, thoſe afflictions, wee bear for Chriſt, and the Goſpel's ſake, make us expreſly par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of Chriſt. For wee are made partakers of Chriſt, if wee hold faſt the beginning of our confidence firm to the end.<note place="margin">Heb 3.14.</note> Therefore John tells us in Rev. 1.9. that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:179792:15"/>he was a brother and companion in tribulation, and in the Kingdome and patience of Chriſt: not in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,<note place="margin">Rev. 1. v. 9.</note> nor effects thereof as perſonal, but as it was myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, in the efficacy thereof: wee bear about in our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies the marks of the Lord Jeſus,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.10. Gal. 6.5.</note> that the life alſo of Chriſt may be made manifeſt in our mortall bodies. Theſe are ſcripture expreſſions for every man ſhall bear his own burthen; to ſin is a great diſhonour, but to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer is not ſo. The Saints are more glorious in being Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, then in being victors.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, becauſe this gives us aſſurance of being glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifyed with Chriſt herafter. Theſe are they which come out of great tribulation; there is an Aſteriſme ſet upon them; ſuch as continue with Chriſt in his tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſhal not onely have a ſeat, but a Throne in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.<note place="margin">1 Thef. 3.3.</note> That no man ſhould be moved by theſe afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for you your ſelves know, that wee are appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thereunto. And through Gods free grace accepting us in and through Jeſus Chriſt; and wee ſuffering, the head and body being united, wee are counted worthy of the Kingdome of God. Then</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> Firſt, from hence let us learn, the eſteem we ſhould have of ſufferings, not onely as they are our duty, but priviledge and honour, he is honourable that gives them to us: now ſeeing wee ſuffer upon Chriſts account, and for his name, that name reflects a great honour upon us; it is a great reproach for a Chriſtian to ſuffer upon his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:179792:16"/>own account: for Chriſt to ſuffer by us, is a great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, but to ſuffer in us is honourable. They rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced that they were counted worthy, to be unworthy; and grac'd to be disgrac'd.<note place="margin">Hebr. 11.38.</note> They that ſuffer for Chriſt are ſuch of whom the world is not worthy. God eſteems heaven a fitter place for them. Conſider what an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable thing it is to ſuffer, 'tis more honourable to give then receive. In all the benedictions of grace con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon us, wee receive from God; in our ſufferings wee give to God. In our ſervices wee doe that which God of us hath commanded; in our ſufferings wee give glory to the cauſe of God to us commended.</p>
               <p>Secondly, bleſs God for any opportunity he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us to ſuffer. Giving thanks to the Father who hath made us meet, to be partakers of the inheritance of the Saints in light:<note place="margin">Col. 1.12.</note> it ſeems a hard leſſon, but 't is to be learn'd, giving thanks to the Father, who by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, have made you meet to be partakers of the inheritance of the Saints in light: for they were made fitt, as by grace, ſo by afflictions. It is a great queſtion, whether wee are moſt to bleſs God for making Heaven fitt for us, or us fitt for Heaven by affliction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="proposition">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:179792:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The fifth Propoſition is this:</hi> That an opportunity to ſuffer for Chriſts name, is to be eſteemed a great privilege and mercy; 't is to be judged the higheſt Felicity.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>5</label> They rejoyced, (the Text ſaith) that they were counted worthy to ſuffer ſhame, for his name. This will be evidenced.</p>
               <p>Firſt, fromthe expreſs command of God to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to ſuffer with joyfullneſs; 't is the general Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter given of the people of God,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.3.</note> they are ſuch as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in Chriſt Jeſus. Wee are of the Circumſion, that worſhip God in the ſpirit, and rejoyce in Chriſt Jeſus.<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1, 2, 3.</note> And wee rejoyce in Chriſt Jeſus, having receiv'd the attonment: And ſo it is the duty and hath been the practiſe of the Saints, to rejoyce in him. Sufferings for Chriſt have been alwayes matter of great joy.<note place="margin">James 1.2.</note> My brethren, count it all joy (ſaith the Apoſtle) when ye fall into divers temptations. Rejoyce and be exceeding glad; for great is your reward in Heaven.<note place="margin">Math. 5.12.</note> Rejoyce ye in that day, when men hath you, and ſeparate you from their company, rejoyce ye in that day, and leap for joy:<note place="margin">Luke 6.22. &amp; 23.</note> for great is your reward in Heaven: for ſo perſecuted they the Prophets. It is the will of God, his people ſhould rejoyce alwayes; rejoyce ever more. 1 Theſſ. 5.16. Eſpecially upon the matters of affliction; that's the will of God towards his people. The Croſs ſhould
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:179792:17"/>not onely be taken up with patience,<note place="margin">Coll. 1.11.</note> but born with joyfullneſs. Strengthened with all might, according to his glorious power, unto all patience, and long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with joyfullneſs: joyfullneſs is a help to patience and long ſuffering under the Croſs. For example, ſee how the Apoſtle rejoyceth under all his afflictions. I rejoyce that I help to fill up that which is behinde of the afflictions of Chriſt in my fleſh,<note place="margin">Col. 1.24.</note> for his bodies ſake which is the Church. But rejoyce in as much as you are partakers of Chriſts ſufferings;<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.13.</note> that when his glory ſhall be reveal'd, ye may be glad wih exceeding joy. In whom beleiving (though under manifold temptations) wee rejoyce with joy unſpeakable and full of glory.<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.8.</note> In a tyme of great affliction it was the great commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Theſſalonians,<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 1, 6.</note> that they received the Goſpel with great joy. The Church rejoyced when the hand of Gods providence was out againſt her. Hab. 3.17, 18. Although the fig-tree ſhould not bloſſom, neither ſhould fruit be in the Vines:<note place="margin">Hab. 3.17, 18.</note> the labour of the Olive ſhould fail, and the fields ſhall yeild no meat: yet will I rejoyce in the Lord, I will joy in the God of my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. And ſo doe the people of God, rejoyce like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe under the ſtroak of mans violence; this hath been their practiſe, nay, not onely to joy, but to glory in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions. Wee glory in tribulation alſo.<note place="margin">Rom. 5.3. 2 Cor. 2.14.</note> Now thanks be unto God, which alwayes cauſeth us to triumph in Chriſt, and maketh manifeſt the ſavour of his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:179792:17"/>by us in every place. A Saint is bound to rejoyce in the Lord in good dayes, and in evil dayes; but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in tymes of great oppoſition.<note place="margin">Neh. 8.10. 2 Cor. 6.10.</note> The joy of the Lord is your ſtrength. As ſorrowfull, yet alway rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing. They tooke joyfully the ſpoyling of their goods Hebr. 10.34. not only patiently, but joyfully.<note place="margin">Acts 16.25. Phil. 1.20.</note> Paul and Silas did not repine, but ſung in the priſon. Paul rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced that Chriſt ſhould be magnified in him whether by life or death. The Martyrs endured exquiſite torments with admirable patience: Divine joy abated outward anguiſh; their ſouls were wrapped up in joy, as if they were in a ſeparated ſtate. Paul counted it his honour to ſuffer reproach and afflictions.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.10.</note> For this cauſe wee both labour, and ſuffer reproach, becauſe wee truſt in the living God. The Apoſtles were not found (in the Text) blaſpheming, nor repining, nor onely ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting but bleſſing God, yea, joying in God: They were not (men) altogether unſenſible of injuries, yet, they that through infirmities foreſooke their Maſter, in the ſtrength of his grace and ſpirit rejoyced to ſuffer for him: remembring Chriſt told them, they were bleſſed that ſuffer. Now there are ſufficient grounds of the Saints thus rejoycing in all their ſufferings.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, in reſpect of the manifold conſolation whereby they are enabled to ſuffer: for as our afflictions abound, ſo our conſolations abound much more by Chriſt Jeſus.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.5.</note> Not onely weight for weight; but a preponderating
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:179792:18"/>weight of conſolation they enjoy: while the people of God drink deep draughts of the water of affliction, they alſo draw water out of the wels of Conſolation. Gods conſolations ought not to be ſmal to his people.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.4, 6.</note>2 Cor. 7.4. compared with the v. 6. Great is my bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſpeech towards you, great is my glorying of you, I am fill'd with comfort, I am exceeding joyfull in all our tribulation, nevertheleſs, God that comforteth thoſe that are caſt down, comforted us by the coming of Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus; though troubled on every ſide: whence aroſe this joy? why, God that comforteth thoſe that are caſt down, comforted us alſo. Though a ſtorme of Haile fell upon their heads, yet the ſun ſhine of his favour ſhone upon their hearts.<note place="margin">Pſal 94.19.</note> In the mid'ſt of my ſad thoughts within me, thy comforts delight my ſoul. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho wee meet with ſtormes without, no matter, ſo wee have but peace within. In the world ye ſhall have tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation (alwayes tribulation) but in me ye ſhall have peace,<note place="margin">John. 16.33.</note> therefore be of good comfort.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, ſufferings for Chriſt's name adminiſters cauſe of rejoycing, becauſe of the ſufficiency of grace adminiſtred under them. My grace is ſufficient for thee, was Chriſt's anſwer to Paul. I have prayed for thee, that thy faith fail not, ſay's he to Peter. Under the ſhaddow of thy wings will I rejoyce, ſaith the Pſalmiſt. Under the ſhaddow of Divine protection and refreſhment.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, there's ground of rejoycing in ſufferings for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:179792:18"/>Chriſt's name, in reſpect of the preſence of God, and Chriſt under afflictions communicated and enjoy'd. Fear not (ſaith God) I am with thee, when thou paſſeſt through the waters I will be with thee:<note place="margin">Iſa. 43.2.</note> and through the rivers they ſhall not overflow thee: when thou paſſeſt through the fire thou ſhalt not be burnt, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall the flame, kindle upon thee. God was with the three Children, when in the fiery-Furnace; with Daniel in the Lyons Den; with Joſeph in the priſon; Jeremiah in the Dungeon. The Lords preſence is with his, to the end of the wold. The preſence of God ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports under all burdens, and ſweetens the bittereſt cups of affliction; you haſt made me more glad, with the light of thy countenance; then they with the encreaſe of their Corn, Wine, and Oyl: Ther's a ſpring in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine joy; if Gods people want the Stars, they ſhall have the light of the Sun: and the enjoyment of God, can make up for the want of the creature.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, another ground of joy, is in reſpect of the aſſurance of deliverance from the greateſt affliction they are under. Who hath delivered us from ſo great a death,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.10.</note> and doth deliver: in whom wee truſt, that he will yet deliver us: Chriſt's deliverance, is an aſſurance to Gods people, of deliverance out of their tribulations: for he that raiſed up our Lord Jeſus from the dead;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.14.</note> by his own power, will alſo raiſe up us. And God hath raiſ'd up the Lord' Chriſt: and will alſo raiſe up us by his
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:179792:19"/>own power. And therefore ye may finde that God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged his people under all their perſecutions; that when their brethren caſt them out for his name ſake, he would take them up, and make their enemies aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, when his hand ſhould be known to his ſervants.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Thirdly, the exceeding great reward of glory pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded may adminiſter ground of joy, and rejoycing under all ſufferings and afflictions. Chriſt for the joy, that was ſet before him, endured the Croſs, and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſhame, and is now ſet down at the right hand of the Majeſty on high.<note place="margin">Heb. 12.2. Heb. 11.27.</note> Moſes haveing a veiw of God, and of glory by the ſpectacles of faith, is ſaid to endure as ſeeing him that is inviſible: for this cauſe wee faint not, but ſuffer reproach, becauſe wee judge that theſe light afflictions, which are but for a moment, worke for us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory. O Soul! who ever thou art, that ſuffereſt for Chriſt's name though hell be behinde thee, Heaven is ſtill before Hell; this was that,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.34.</note> thoſe primitive Chriſtians comforted themſelves with. Knowing with in themſelves (they had experience in their own hearts, aſſurance in their boſoms) that in Heaven they had a better and more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during ſubſtance.<note place="margin">40 Mart.</note> This comforted thoſe fourty Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, when (before they were to ſuffer) they were caſt in to water in cold weather; now (ſay they) we ſhake for cold, but by and by we ſhall be in Abrahams boſom: men may kill the Saints, but it is impoſſible that they
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:179792:19"/>ſhould ever hurt them: ſo that an opportunity to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for Chriſt is to be eſteemed as a meecy. By way of inference from hence.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> Firſt, take notice of the ſtrength and power of divine grace, that is able to make a man ſuffer contentedly and joyfully; 't will make a Chriſtian go through good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and evill report.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, from hence I may obſerve (likewiſe) the great abatement, degeneracy, and timerouſneſs of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that is in Profeſſors of Religion in theſe latter dayes; the Saints in former tymes accounted it an honour to ſuffer Chriſt; wee account it a burden, wee are back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; wee are ready to cry out undone, if it comes to a little of our Eſtate, liberty or name: if ever God call us out to ſuffering, ſurely he will grant us more grace, elſe were ſhall ſhamefully diſhonour him. O thou ſpirit of Chriſtianity! where art thou become? O thou holy joy (in ſufferings!) where art thou? It is for a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, and ſhall be for a lamentation to think On theſe things.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, hence obſerve, the vaſt difference there is between Saints and ſinners; the Saints can rejoyced in ſufferings, ſo can't the wicked. The heart knweth its own bitterneſs, and a ſtranger doth not intermedle with his joy. This is a joy no ſgranger intermedles with:<note place="margin">Prov. 14.10.</note> the world wonders how the Saints go ſo courageouſly through ſufferings. But the Martyrs anſwer may ſerve
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:179792:20"/>to anſwer this; yee ſee the fewel that burns me, but did yee feel the joy that I feel, ye would not wonder. The wayes, of ſin is death, but the gift of God is eternall life, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord: eternall life is ſweet, the aſſured expectation whereof makes men thus to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. There is a great deal of difference between Saints and ſinners upon this account.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2ly."/> Secondly, from hence I might ſpeak matter of juſt reproofe to the Saints and people of God, that are ſo far from this frame and temper, to rejoyce in ſuffering for Chriſts name. You ought to be joyfull in tribulation; but I fear many of you are not patient under the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Goſpel. Were they joyfull under the burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing coals of Juniper, and ſhall not wee be patient, (at leaſt) under leſſer ſufferings? Diſpondency is a ſin as well as murmuring and repineing. What an diſhonour is it to God to murmur under affliction?</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, what an diſhonour is this to Jeſus Chriſt, to be dedolent under ſufferings? when ſervices and ſufferings come of heavyly, itmuſt needs be a diſhonour to Chriſt: It is a diſhonour to a Chaptaine, if his Souldiers march on heavyly.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 19:2, 4.</note> I may allude to that 2 Sam. 19:2, 4. where the King wept for his ſon, and the victory that day was turned into mourning, and the King covered his face and cryed with a loud voice, O my ſon Abſalom, O Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolom, my ſon,<note place="margin">NUm. 14.2.</note> my ſon: wat an ugly ſight was that of the Iſralites digging their graves. And all the Children
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:179792:20"/>of Iſrael murmured againſt Moſes, and againſt Aaron: and againſt the whole congregation, and ſaid unto them, would, God that wee had died in the Land of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, or would God wee had died in this wilderneſs. It is a great ſhame for Chriſtians, and it is a great diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to Chriſt, for Chriſtians to be ſo daſtardly ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, conſider what an unworthy returne is this to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ſuffered ſo much, and ſo willingly for us. I am ſtraitned with in me till this bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme be accompliſhed (ſaith Chrit.) It was no trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Chriſt that he was to die, but raither that he died no ſooner. And ſhall wee thus returne evill to him for his good to us? Shall wee think much to bear the prick of a pin for him, that was peirced with a ſpear for us?</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Thirdly, what a diſcouragement does this offer to profeſſion and Religion in the world; it lay's a ſtumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-block before many that would fall in with Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but that they think there is but little in it, elſe the Profeſſors of it, would ſuffer more for it: If a ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard-bearer in an Army his heart fail, it offers a great diſcouragement to the common Souldier: goe on there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore courageouſly in the profeſſion of holyneſs. The contrary God threatens to his Enemies, to Aſſiria the rod of his anger when he breaks them in peice. Iſa. 10.18. And they ſhall be as when a ſtandard-bearer fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.<note place="margin">Iſa. 10.18, 19.</note> And then the reſt of the trees of his forreſt ſhall be
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:179792:21"/>few, that a Child may write them. When the hearts of the principall of God flock faile, they offer diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement to all the reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, it ſpoiles the acceptance of all your other ſervices; it ſpoiles Gods acceptance of all your duties and ſervices: God will not accept a doer, if he be not (at leaſt) willing, to be a ſufferer, and that rejoyceing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; God can't endure a man ſuffering (ſo to ſpeak) with a blur'd face, hanging down his head like a bull-ruſh. Chriſts active obedience could not doe alone in point of ſatisfaction, nor can ours in point of duty.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<note n="2" place="margin">2ly for reproof.</note> this juſtly reproves thoſe, that, inſteed of rejoyceing to ſuffer for Chriſt, entertaines them with regrate, that come to affliction as a bear to the ſtake, or a theef to the Gallous. Such as ſhrinke, eſpecially that dog it in Religion when they ſhould appear courage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, ſuch ſufferings are very unacceptable unto God, when (wee are compell'd to that, in which wee ſhould be moſt free and voluntary.<note place="margin">Iſa. 58.5.</note> Is it ſuch a Faſt that I have choſen? a day for a man to afflict his ſoul? is it to bow down his head like a bull-ruſh, and to ſpread ſackcloth and aſhes under him? wilt thou call this a Faſt, and an acceptable day unto the Lord? It is a ſad ſigne of a perverſe and hypocriticall heart, not to ſuffer joyfully upon Chriſts account. The Romans, if the beaſt that was to be made a ſacrifice would not goe willingly, they would never offer that beaſt up in ſacrifice; ſo if
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:179792:21"/>wee doe not offer our ſelves willingly, ſoul and body, which is but our reaſonable ſacrifice, we ſhall not be accounted holy, nor acceptable to God through Jeſus Chriſt. It was the excellencie of former tymes,<note place="margin">4 Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions anent ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings.</note> that they were carefull to ſuffer for Chriſt, that ſo Chriſt might not ſuffer by them. Alwayes remember.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that it is far better to ſuffer for Chriſt, then to ſuffer by Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Caut. </seg>2</label> Secondly, remember how much Chriſt ſuffered for you. The juſt for the unjuſt, that he might bring us to God. I remember the Souldier told Auguſtus,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.10.</note> if I had ſerved you, as you ſerve me, at the battel of Actium, where had you been? ſo may Chriſt ſay to us, where had you been, if I had ſerved you upon the Croſs, as ye ſerve me? if I had deſerted your cauſe, what had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of you? ye had been loſt to eternity.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Caut. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, conſider, wee partake of Chriſts ſufferings proportionably, as he partakes of ours. If we ſuffer for him, his ſufferings are made manifeſt in us.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Caut. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, he that by directly unlawfull means will endeavour to avoid ſufferings, commonly runs upon a double ſuffering; is expoſed to ſufferings both in body and ſoul, in time, and it may be to eternity.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, by way of exhortation,<note n="3" place="margin">3 For Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> let me perſwade all of you, to learn this Leſlen (though hard, and will goe much againſt the hair, of holy joyfullneſs in ſufferings; it is good for you to be provided, and not to goe naked
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:179792:22"/>into a ſtorme and battel; hard tymes put me upon call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you to it. Since Chriſt hath ſuffered for us, arme your ſelves likewiſe with the ſame minde: reſolve to ſuffer with chearfullneſs: 't is your priviledge as well as duty: why will yee neglect one thing that is matter of privilege unto you?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Motives 8.</note> Motives to preſs you hereunto.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Mot. </seg>1</label> Firſt; It is an Evidence of Saint-ſhip, of truth of grace, and of ſtrength of grace; and the want of it is an evidence of Hypocriſie. For where in will yee diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence your ſelves from ſinners and ungodly? They are confounded under their temptations and ſorrowfull un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their afflictions; and if you can't rejoyce under af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, what ſingular thing doe you.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Mot. </seg>2</label> Secondly, conſider your afflictions and ſufferings have no real evil in them, and all the happineſs of the world is no more, then what your Fancies put upon them. They are but imaginary excellencies, it is onely an ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary happineſs that is in the world, and all theſe things.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Mot. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, all your afflictions (though inflicted by men) are ordered by God, and his wiſe providence; they are appointed by your heavenly Father, and ſhall I not drink the Cup, that my Father hath given me to drink, ſaith Chriſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Mot. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, they are all conſiſtant with Gods fatherly
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:179792:22"/>love; yea, while he ſuffers wicked men to chaſtiſe and correct you, his fatherly love is towards you: Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have had powerfull experience, and familiar ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance of and with God upon this account: God as a Father chaſtiſeth every Son whom he receiveth; nay, as the fyre burns hotteſt, when the wether is coldeſt, ſo Gods affections to his people is higheſt; when their afflictions are greateſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Mat. </seg>5</label> Fiftly, conſider all your tryalls tend to the advance of grace, and the purging out of your corruptions, for the refineing of your grace.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.16.</note> For this cauſe wee faint not; (ſaith the Apoſtle) for though our outward man periſh, our inward man is renewed day by day, as the Sea, what it looſeth in one ſhiere, it gets in another: grace grows by an Antiperiſtaſis, affliction is ſanctified and grace is exerciſed and proved thereby. Wee had fathers of our fleſh, that corrected us; and wee gave them reverence: ſhall we not much rather be in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection unto the father of ſpirits, and live?<note place="margin">Heb. 12.9. and 10.</note> They cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected us for their pleaſure, but he for our profit, that wee might be partakers of his holyneſs. The tryal of your faith is for honour, praiſe and glory: fiery tryals make golden Chriſtians, your ſuffering (like the ſun) ſcorcheth the Hypocrite, but ripens the ſincere Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. The North-winde of affliction, blowing upon the garden of the ſaints graces, cauſe the ſpices thereof to flow forth.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:179792:23"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Mot. </seg>6</label> Sixthly,<note place="margin">Math. 5.11, 12</note> Bleſſedneſs is the entail; Math. 5.11, 12. bleſſed are yee, when men ſhall revile yow, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute you; rejoyce and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in heaven.<note place="margin">Luke 6.22, 23.</note> Bleſſed are ye when men ſhall hate you, and when they ſhall ſeparate you from their company, and ſhall reproach yow, and caſt out your name as evil, for the ſon of mans ſake. Rejoyce yee in that day,<note place="margin">Luke 6.23.</note> and leap for joy: for behold your reward is great in heaven: for in the like manner did their fathers unto the Prophets. Happy are they that endure.</p>
               <p>Seventhly,<note place="margin">James 5.11. Mot. 7.</note> all your ſufferings ſerve to work you up to a further likeneſs to Chriſt and the ſaints. Soe they dealt with them before you. Take, my brethren, the Prophets,<note place="margin">James 5.10.</note> who have ſpoken in the name of the Lord, for an example of ſuffering affliction, and of patience.</p>
               <p>Eightly,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.35.</note> they greaten and agravate your glory and happineſs in the next world. They would not accept of deliverance, that they might obtain a better reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. They had a good reſurrection, though they had not ſuffered, but hereby they had a better one. O that all might prevail with you to this rejoyceing! if yee may be counted worthy to ſuffer ſhame for Chriſts name. Now your joy under ſufferings muſt be.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="1" place="margin">1. What kind of joy yee muſt leave.</note>Firſt, ſpiritual, not carnal, in ſpiritual objects, in things ſpiritual; it muſt be a pure and refined joy. Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus rejoyced in ſpirit. Luke 10.21. The joy of the Lord muſt be your ſtrength: your joy muſt be pure and ſpirituall.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:179792:23"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, a ſerious, not a light frothy joy,<note place="margin">Hebr. 12.5.</note> we muſt glory, not ſport it under afflictions and tribulations. Wee muſt not diſpond, nor yet make light of afflictions; if we make light of afflictions, God will make them heavy, true joy ſhould be a ſerious thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, it muſt be a practicall joy,<note place="margin">Luke 6.23.</note> puting the ſoul on to duty, engageing the ſoul under all afflictions to manifeſt our joy by outward ſignes; a leaping of heart and body, it comes from, and is an alluſion to the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceing of the Galyard, or leaping of young cattel that are wanton, or (as ſome carry it) to the joy that a Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom takes in his Bride, upon their marriage day.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, it muſt not be a paſſionate and tranſient, but a permanent and laſting joy; they rejoyced in Chriſts light for a tyme, but when perſecution came, they were offended. Moſes was faithfull over all his houſe as a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant; but Chriſt as a ſon, whoſe houſe wee are, if wee hold faſt the beginning of our confidence, and the rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceing of hope, firme to the end.<note place="margin">Heb. 3.6.</note> Strengthened with all might to endure with patience, and long ſuffering with joyfullneſs. Our joy muſt be ſuch as the Apoſtles was here, they were conſtant; that accompanied their joy. A ſaint indeed may have ſome mixtures of ſadneſs; but though heavyneſs endure for a night, joy comes in the morning. A beleivers joy is not like that of a hypocrite that laſts but for a moment: but conſtant: like the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict of winde and fire, that encreaſeth it the more; ſo
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:179792:24"/>muſt afflictions. That Apoſtle that failed before in his ſpeeches and doctrine, could now rejoyce in his ſtripes; he that before trembled at the look of a ſilly damſel, now could look upon the face of a great and learned Councel. But you will ſay,<note place="margin">10. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect. and Helps.</note> what ſhall wee doe, to attaine ſuch a bleſſed frame of ſpirit? I will propound you ſome dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to help you herein.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct.  </seg>1</label> Firſt,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.12.</note> if yee would be joyfull under your ſufferings for Chriſts ſake, Enure your ſelves to them; count not the fiery tryall a ſtrange thing wee entertaine ſtrangers with diſſatisfaction, but friends with joy and delight: receive not ſufferings as ſtrangers, but friends, and then yee will bid them welcome; wee are like Ephraim unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to the yoak, and that maks us to entertaine afflictions ſo unwillingly. A ſuit at firſt puting on, pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches but afterward becomes eaſie; a Bird at firſt puting into the Cage is dampiſh, but afterwards being ſatisfied ſings ſweetly;<note place="margin">Fox: vol. 2. pag. 277.</note> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Bilney in priſon divers times proved the fire, by putting his finger near to the candle; at the firſt touch of the candle his fleſh reſiſting, and he with drawing his finger, did after chide his fleſh in theſe words; <hi>Quid unius membri inuſtionem ferre non potes, &amp; quo pacto cras totius corporis conflagrationem tolerabis?</hi> What (ſaid he) canſt thou not bear the burning of one mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and how wilt thou endure to morrow the burning of the whole body? I feel, and have known it long by philoſophy, that fire is hot; yet I know ſome (recorded
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:179792:24"/>in Gods word) even in the flame felt no heat; and I believe that though my body will be waſted by it, my ſoul ſhall be purged thereby.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>2</label> Secondly, be ſure ye ſuffer upon good grounds, ſuffer warrantably, and innocently; warrantably, when you muſt either ſin or ſuffer, or when the Truth muſt ſuffer for want of your Teſtimony; Innocently, ſanctifie the Lord God in your hearts, and make him your fear and your dread; and be ready to give an anſwer to every one, of the hope that is in you; be ſure ye ſuffer with a good conſcience; 't is the winde in the bowels of the earth, that cauſeth the Earth-quake: Innocency is an excellent Target under ſufferings. A Roman Lady being carried to priſon, when great with child, when the tyme of her travail came, cried out much; ſayes the Jaylor to her, what ails you, how will you burn, or bear it to be prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the point of a ſword? O! quoth she now I ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer as a malefactor, then I ſhall ſuffer as a Martyr. Look you have no ſin in your ſufferings, if ye would have joy, I have read of many, that have for fear, or love of the world, turn'd back and apoſtatized, yet their perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors would make them ſuffer, and they did it with great trouble; Labour to be able to ſay, Lord 't is not ſo much for mine as thy ſake that I ſuffer.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>3</label> Tirdly, if ſo be ye would ſuffer for the name of Chriſt, get a right underſtanding of the croſs; look on both ſides of ſuffering, obſerve the ſharpneſs on the one,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:179792:25"/>and yet the ſweetneſs on the other hand. I have read of a picture, that had the deformed ſhape of a Monſter on the one ſide, and the face of a beautifull virgin on the other: ſo are ſufferings, black on one ſide and beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full on the other; when wee judge of the Bee by her ſting wee can't bear with her, but conſider honey with it, and ſhe is acceptable. Remember the joyfullneſs of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, as well as the grieviouſneſs of them, and you will be taken off all prejudices againſt it. Tribulation works patience, and patience experience, and experience hope, and hope maketh not aſhamed; becauſe the love of God is ſhed abroad in our hearts by the holy Ghoſt: God gives all out of love in proportion, and in infinite wiſdome, which he will ſhew in due tyme. The ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomed of the Lord ſhall come to Zion, and everlaſting joy ſhall be upon their hands, though now they have ſorrow in their hearts.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>4</label> Fourthly,<note place="margin">Rev. 2.2. comp. with 3.</note> if you would ſuffer joyfully for Chriſt, then labour for joy in doing work, this will make way for joy in ſuffering Rev. 2.2, &amp; 3. compared. I know thy works and thy labour, and thy patience, and for my name ſake haſt laboured and haſt not fainted; the ſoul that comes once to worke and labour, will come to patience, and will not faint: if ye would bear Chriſts Croſs joyfully,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.8. &amp; 9.</note> labour to bear his yoak joyfully; for bodily exerciſe profiteth little, but godlyneſs is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable unto all things; having the promiſe of the life
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:179792:25"/>that now is, and of that which is to come. This is a faithfull ſaying and worthy of all acceptation. I count not my life dear unto my ſelf, ſo that I might finiſh my courſe with joy, and the Miniſtry which I have recived of the Lord Jeſus,<note place="margin">Acts 20.24.</note> to teſtifie the Goſpel of the grace of God; what follows! but I am willing to die at Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem for the name of Jeſus.<note place="margin">Pſ. 119.114.</note> Thou art my hiding place and my ſhield I hope in thy word. He made the word the man of his Counſels; and ſo it was the man of his comforts.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, labour to get a right eſteem of ſufferings, eſteem them as a priviledge, an honour as well as a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that will make you ſuffer joyfully, ye muſt not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly look to your innocency, to take heed that you ſuffer not from God, while you ſuffer for God: but turne your afflictions into a right ſtream and channell, to us it is given (ſaith the Apoſtle) not onely to beleive, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to ſuffer for his ſake, he looked upon it as a Largeſs. Chryſoſt. ſaith of Paul, that he boaſts moſt of this, I Paul the priſoner of the Lord: he does not boaſt of his high offices, knowledge of arts and ſciences, great and glorious Revelations, no, but the glories in his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as in his own narrative it appeares.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.23. ad finem capitis.</note> 2 Cor. 11:23. in labours more aboundant: in ſtripes above meaſure: in priſons more frequent: in death oft, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, take heed of conſulting with fleſh and blood; the fleſh is a jade that will kick at ſufferings; when
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:179792:26"/>Peter grew carnal and fleſhly, his voice was no better then this, Maſter ſave thy ſelf: which motion Chriſt rejected, with a get thee behinde me Satan. Looke not at the making of your own Intereſt; but advance the Intereſt of Chriſt and the Goſpel; your endeavours to ſave your own ſelves, will but make you ſtumble at the Croſs of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>7</label> Seaventhly, labour for a double portion of the Spirit of grace, of love and of a ſound minde. This is our victory whereby wee overcome the world, even our faith; love is as ſtrong as death, as powerfull as the grave, the waters of affliction cannot quench, but will enflame it; 't will make you choſe (as Moſes did) rather to ſuffer affliction with the people of God, then to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the pleaſures of ſin, which are but for a ſeaſon.</p>
               <p>Eightly,<note place="margin">Direct. 8. 1 Cor. 15.31. Heb. 13.13. 1 Cor. 7.30.</note> take heed of being overcome with love to the world. I proteſt by your rejoyceing which I have in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, I die dayly. Wee muſt goe forth unto Chriſt without the Camp, bearing his reproach. If wee would rejoyce in the world, it muſt be as if wee rejoyced not, and if wee buy, as if wee poſſeſſed not. Our rejoyceing ſhould be in God, not in the world for the faſhion thereof paſſeth away; in a day of proſperity wee are too apt to be fil'd with carnall joy;<note place="margin">Gal. 6.14.</note> and oft tymes wee have the more heavenly joy in God in a day of Adverſity. God forbid I ſhould glory in any thing ſave in the Croſs of Chriſt, whereby the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:179792:26"/>world is crucified unto me, and I am crucified unto the world. A holy contempt of the world, will beſt lead you to a holy joy in God.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>9</label> Ninthly, be much in the conſideration of Heaven, that will make amends fot all your ſufferings on earth; thou ſhalt make me glad, with the light of thy counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, thou wilt ſhew me the path of life; in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is fullneſs of joy, at they right hand there are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for ever more. And in the Acts 2.25, 26. it is ſaid of David in the perſon of Chriſt;<note place="margin">Pſal. 16. ult.</note> that he foreſaw the Lord alwayes before his face, therefore did my heart re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and my tongue was glad, moreover alſo my fleſh ſhall reſt in hope. O the bleſſed enjoyment of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for the next world! the glorious viſion and frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God, that is to be enjoy'd in heaven; the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that is to be enjoyed with the glorious Angels and Saints in Heaven, will ſweeten all. Rejoyce that your names are written in Heaven.<note place="margin">Luke 10.20.</note> Luke 10.20. in the Lambs book of life; if your names are written in blood or in water in the worlds Calander, yet they are written in gold in the Lambs book of life; with in a few dayes, you ſhall enter into your Maſters joy. I reckon not the ſufferings of this preſent tyme worthy to be compared to the glory that is to be revealed in us: Look upon ſin and hell, and then ſufferings and heaven will appear the higheſt good. I read of one that ſpent his tyme in read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of three leaves; the black leafe of his own ſins;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:179792:27"/>the red leafe of Chriſts blood, and the white leafe of Heaven and Eternity. Three leafes worth the reading of. For this cauſe wee faint not, while wee looke not at the things which are ſeen and temporall; but at thoſe things which are not ſeen, but eternall. Labour to make a right compariſon between the horrour of hell, and the happineſs of Heaven: get a greater aſſurance of Heaven,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.3.</note> that ye may rejoyce in the hope that is laid up for you in Heaven. This was that, thoſe ſcattered Sants bleſſed God for. Bleſſed be the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: which according to his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundant mercy, hath begotten us againe unto a lively hope, by the reſurrecton of Jeſus Chriſt from the dead. To an inheritance incorruptable and undefiled that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not away, reſerved in heaven for you. This made them breake out into a triumphant doxology; this made the Martyrs hearts leap for joy under their ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings for Chriſt, even the thoughts of Heaven and that bleſſed eternity to which they were going; holy Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius triumphed going to ſuffer at Rome; yea, gloried and triumphed to think that the Lord would come to reckon for blood.</p>
               <p>Tenthtly, and laſtly, labour to get your hearts diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged of carnall and ſlaviſh fear, perfect love caſteth out fear; be not affraid to die, and you will not be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to ſuffer. Yee may threſh the body of a poor man, but yee cannot hurt the jewel of his ſoul. Threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:179792:27"/>ſaith the Emperour what yee will, I fear nothing but ſin; fear not them that can kill the body, and after that have no more that they can doe; but I will fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warn you whom yee ſhould fear: fear him that when he hath kill'd, hath power to deſtroy both body and ſoul in hell fire. Why ſhoul'ſt thou fear a mortall man, that hath his breath in his Noſtrils, or his bigg words, or ſtaring face? doe men threaten impriſonment? God threatens hell. Doe they promiſe great rewards, if ye will but comply with them? Aske them (as the Father did) whether they can give that to you they would take from you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="proposition">
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſixt Propoſition is this.</hi> That the Conſideration of Chriſts name, that is concern'd in the ſufferings of the Saints, is ſufficient, to encourage them under them.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>6</label> They rejoyced, they were counted worthy to ſuffer ſhame for his name ſake; not for their own name. The great ground of joy under ſufferings is Chriſts name.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.11.</note> For wee which live are alwayes delivered unto death for Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſake, that the life alſo of Jeſus might be made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in our mortall fleſh. Chriſts blood is the meritorious cauſe, and his ſpirit and grace the aſſiſting cauſe, and when ſufferings come from his name ſake as the procur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cauſe there is alwayes joy in them. Therefore
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:179792:28"/>when wee ſuffer for bearing witneſs to the Truth, this is ſuffering for Chriſts name; when wee thus hold forth the profeſſion of Chriſts name, it tends to the glory of Chriſt. When wee ſuffer out of Love to Chriſts honour to his perſon, love to his offices and adminiſtrations, chooſeing to ſuffer rather then to abate any duty, or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect any communion, when wee ſuffer upon a Goſpel account, as Chriſt ſuffered for the introduction, ſo wee for the confirmation, as he for the ſatisfaction, ſo wee for the edification of the Church, that is the valuable account of our ſufferings:<note place="margin">Phil. 2.17.</note> this the Apoſtle triumphed in Phil. 2.17. there he tells them If I be offered upon the ſacrifice and ſervice of your Faith, I ioy and rejoyce with you all. There is great reaſon why this ſhould encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the hearts of Gods people under all their ſufferings, becauſe it is but a juſt returne to him of his ſufferings for us: it entails us to great honour with him; and he is able to recompence us for them all.<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 1.7.</note> 2 Theſſ. 1.7. And to you who are troubled reſt with us, when the Lord Jeſus ſhall be revealed from heaven with his mighty Angels. To cloſe all hence.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> Firſt, Learn the different excellency there is between the ſuffering of the Goſpel, and all other ſufferings. Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings for ſin are a cauſe of ſorrow rather then joy, ſome corrections are for ſin, ſome for the tryall and probation of grace; ſome for bearing witneſs to the Truth. In cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for ſin, wee may have comfort; if born patiently,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:179792:28"/>and ſubmiſſively, juſtifying of God and condemning of our ſelf, and humbling our ſelves for the ſin, that was the provoking cauſe of them: there is comfort in thoſe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, that are for the tryall and probation of grace, 't will be found for honour and praiſe at the appearing of Jeſus Chriſt:<note place="margin">Luke 21.13.</note> But under ſufferings for Chriſt's name much more; This will turne to you for a teſtimony. If wee ſuffer as evill doers, our ſufferings are not thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie, but if wee ſuffer wrongfully happy are wee.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, by way of encouragement, let us not be affraid, nor aſhamed of the afflictions of the Goſpel, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, becauſe they are upon the account of the precious name of Chriſt: no matter though we be diſgraced, ſo Chriſt may be honoured, if our names be cutt out, ſo Chriſt may be exalted. The Church and people of God may encourage themſelves, that they have the name of Chriſt to bear it out with, even that name by which the whole family in heaven and earth is named. Saith Calvin, let Luther call me Devil, ſo Chriſt may be magnified by me I care not: many will be fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to ſuffer upon the account of a temporall Prince and Agent: and account themſelves honoured thereby, how much more honourable is it to ſuffer for the Prince of life, and glory?</p>
               <p>Thirdly how precious ought Chriſts name to be to the ſaints; if it will make ſufferings ſo ſweet; what will it not make ſweet? how precious muſt that name needs
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:179792:29"/>be, that wee are concern'd to lay down our names and lives for, if call'd for? O how ſweet is the name of Chriſt? it will like a bunch of Camphire ſweeten all to us. Let us eſteem of that bleſſed name, and count all loſs and droſs, yea, and dung for the excellency of the knowledge of it.<note place="margin">Cant. 1.3.</note> Cant. 1.3. Becauſe of the ſavour of thy good oyntments thy name is as an oyntment poured forth, therefore doe the Virgins love thee. To ſuch as beleive Chriſts name is precious. He is admired of his ſaints, and of all them that beleive. Nothing ſhall ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate me (ſaith the Apoſtle) from the love of God; which is in Chriſt Jeſus. If wee love that name, wee ſhall not onely be ready to be bound, but to die at Jeruſalem, for the name of Jeſus; rather chooſing the communion of Gods people, and the afflicted ſtate thereof, then all the pleaſures of ſin, which are but for a ſeaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
